<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>samoan-passage | Gunnar Voet</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/tags/samoan-passage/</link><atom:link href="https://gunnarvoet.github.io/tags/samoan-passage/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>samoan-passage</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Gunnar Voet</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2019 22:07:26 -0700</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/images/icon_hud692a76e5d31a98a8df50b31c984ca7f_48833_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>samoan-passage</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/tags/samoan-passage/</link></image><item><title>A Step Beyond</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/post/a-step-beyond/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2019 22:07:26 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/post/a-step-beyond/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today I had the opportunity to participate in an unusual class setting: At
&lt;a href="https://a-step-beyond.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A Step Beyond&lt;/a> in Escondido, CA, I talked to 5th and 6th graders about some of the observational methods we use in physical oceanography. In between the lessons, the students, together with their dance teacher Roxanne Rojas de Blanco, came up with dance moves to transform what they had just learned into a choreography. With a lot of creative energy the students danced ships in stormy seas and subsurface moorings knocked over by strong currents. Many thanks to Roxanne and my colleague Larry Pratt from WHOI for organizing this workshop and to the National Science Foundation for financial support through our Samoan Passage research project!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-larry-pratt-explaining-the-origins-of-water-on-earth-to-the-class">
&lt;a data-fancybox="" href="https://gunnarvoet.github.io/post/a-step-beyond/larry_hub93307cc1f30c6a9f5062110219cd2ff_1216253_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg" data-caption="Larry Pratt explaining the origins of water on earth to the class.">
&lt;img data-src="https://gunnarvoet.github.io/post/a-step-beyond/larry_hub93307cc1f30c6a9f5062110219cd2ff_1216253_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg" class="lazyload" alt="" width="3148" height="2159">
&lt;/a>
&lt;figcaption>
Larry Pratt explaining the origins of water on earth to the class.
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure></description></item><item><title>Persistent Turbulence in the Samoan Passage</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/publication/journal-article/cusack-etal-2019/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/publication/journal-article/cusack-etal-2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Pacific Abyssal Transport and Mixing: Through the Samoan Passage versus around the Manihiki Plateau</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/publication/journal-article/pratt-et-al-2019/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/publication/journal-article/pratt-et-al-2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Hydraulic Processes in the Samoan Passage</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/hyprsp/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/hyprsp/</guid><description>&lt;p>We just got funded by NSF to study abyssal hydraulic processes in the Samoan Passage. The project will heavily build upon data collected in the
&lt;a href="https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/samoan-passage/">Samoan Passage Abyssal Mixing Experiment&lt;/a>. In addition, we are planning on running a suite of numerical models spanning from idealized 2D to high-resolution 3D runs that will be tuned to observed turbulent mixing. This dataset will help us identify and study a number of processes that are loosely termed &lt;em>hydraulic&lt;/em> - they arise when bottom topography restricts the free flow of the bottom current. Hydraulic processes may cause and alter turbulent mixing of the abyssal current with ambient water and impose restrictions on the maximum flow through the Samoan Passage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Present theory is unable to account for a number of hydraulic aspects that let the flow through Samoan Passage stand out. Among these are flow through connecting channels, flow through channels with two sill configurations and flow across sills with complex bathymetry. Getting a handle on these processes will be important for better understanding the large scale circulation of the Pacific Ocean as the Samoan Passage is the major supplier for deep water renewal in the North Pacific. Moreover, these configurations are by no means unique to the flow through Samoan Passage and a better knowledge of hydraulic processes here will inform research of the flow at many other canyons and fracture zones of the world&amp;rsquo;s oceans.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Warming and Weakening of the flow through Samoan Passage</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/publication/journal-article/samoan-passage-warming-weakening/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/publication/journal-article/samoan-passage-warming-weakening/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Pathways, Volume Transport and Mixing of Abyssal Water in the Samoan Passage</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/publication/journal-article/samoan-passage-pathways-mixing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/publication/journal-article/samoan-passage-pathways-mixing/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Turbulent mixing and hydraulic control of abyssal water in the Samoan Passage</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/publication/journal-article/samoan-passage-mixing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/publication/journal-article/samoan-passage-mixing/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Samoan Passage Abyssal Mixing Experiment</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/samoan-passage/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/samoan-passage/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Samoan Passage is the major gateway for deep water renewal in the North Pacific where virtually no bottom waters are formed locally. About 6 Sv (1 Sv $\equiv 1 \times 10^6$ m$^3$ s$^{-1}$), more than half of the abyssal northward limb of the Pacific Meridional Overturning Circulation (MOC), flows through the Samoan Passage while smaller amounts flow across Robbie Ridge to the west and around the Manihiki Plateau to the east. As the bottom current is forced through the narrow channels and across the sills of the Samoan Passage it is strongly modified by turbulent mixing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In our recent NSF-funded &lt;em>Samoan Passage Abyssal Mixing Experiment&lt;/em> we gathered moored and shipboard measurements to re-assess the long term volume transport through the Samoan Passage and to study flow pathways and turbulent mixing processes in the Samoan Passage. Moored long-term observations of the abyssal flow through the Samoan Passage, when compared to historical measurements, showed a slightly weakened volume transport by about 0.6 Sv or 10% and a significant warming of $1\times10^{-3}$ K/yr over the past two decades. Shipboard CTD/LADCP sections from a cruise in 2012 revealed the flow pathways through the Samoan Passage with the unanticipated result of about half the volume transport going through shallower channels to the west while the other, denser, half goes through the main eastern channel. Topographic sills along both pathways lead to hydraulic response and strong associated acceleration and mixing of the flow. Detailed measurements at the primary sill of the eastern channelw showed flow acceleration to more than 0.5 m/s. The first direct turbulence measurements with an autonomous Vertical Microstructure Profiler in the Samoan Passage revealed 1000 to 10,000 times stronger turbulence than oceanographic background levels. Heat-budget derived estimates of turbulent mixing levels were 2 to 6 times higher than area-averaged mixing levels in the Samoan Passage, pointing to the importance of mixing concentrated at so-called hot-spots. These mixing hot-spots are located downstream of the sills, where the flow, likely hydraulically controlled, accelerates, and hydraulic jumps with the highest mixing levels in the region were observed.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>