<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects | Gunnar Voet</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/</link><atom:link href="https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Projects</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Gunnar Voet</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/images/icon_hud692a76e5d31a98a8df50b31c984ca7f_48833_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Projects</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/</link></image><item><title>Mixing Below Tropical Instability Waves</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/tiw/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/tiw/</guid><description>&lt;p>The equatorial Pacific Ocean is a key region for the El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO). Commonly known as the two siblings El Niño and La Niña, ENSO is a complex interplay of oceanic and atmospheric dynamics that influences communities surrounding the Pacific Ocean and beyond. While there has been tremendous progress in the understanding of the ENSO phenomenon over the past few decades, which has led to the ability to forecast ENSO conditions over the time span of several months, the detailed processes driving and modifying ENSO are not very well understood yet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The cold tongue of the eastern equatorial Pacific Ocean plays a critical role in driving and modifying ENSO conditions. It can become unstable and form tropical instability waves (TIWs) that extend several hundred kilometers away from the equator (see the figure at the top for an example of the cold tongue and how it forms waves). Recent studies have indicated that turbulent mixing in the ocean, caused by TIWs directly at the equator, plays an important role for the heat budget of the cold tongue with important implications for ENSO. TIWs are much more prevalent during La Niña conditions when the cold tongue is more pronounced than during El Niño or neutral ENSO years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this project funded by the National Science Foundation we aim at studying turbulent mixing processes away from the equator (within about 5°) that may be associated with TIW fronts through their potential for creating or modifying internal waves. The generation of internal waves, or modification of incoming internal waves generated elsewhere, may lead to increased velocity shear which in turn can provide a route to wave breaking and turbulent mixing. Preliminary results from Argo float data show a correlation between elevated turbulent mixing well below the thermocline and stronger TIW activity during La Niña years. Using a combination of yearlong moored observations and two dedicated cruises in 2023 and 2024 where we will bring the MOD fastCTD, Epsifish, and drifting Wirewalkers, we will collect data at TIW fronts that will help us better understand internal wave dynamics associated with the fronts and how they may lead to ocean turbulence and the turbulent transport of heat within the ocean.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The project is a collaboration between Caitlin Whalen at APL/UW, Jim Moum at OSU, and Amy Waterhouse &amp;amp; Gunnar Voet at Scripps.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Boundary Layer Turbulence - BLT</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/blt/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/blt/</guid><description>&lt;p>Turbulence and abyssal upwelling in deep bottom boundary layers. More to come soon!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Near-Inertial Shear and Kinetic Energy in the North Atlantic Experiment - NISKINe</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/niskine/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/niskine/</guid><description>&lt;p>Variable winds at the ocean surface can force motions inside the ocean that oscillate at frequencies set by the local component of the earth&amp;rsquo;s rotation rate. Motions at these near-inertial frequencies, so called near-inertial waves, dominate upper ocean shear and contribute to upper ocean turbulence. Their generation, evolution and decay still remain poorly understood. Recent advances in theory and numerical modeling have pointed to interactions of near-inertial waves with mesoscale and submescoscale features.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-schematic-showing-processes-associated-with-near-inertial-generation-dissipation-and-propagation-as-storms-move-along-the-storm-track-thick-white-arrow-a-local-response-occurs-with-frequencies-near-the-local-coriolis-frequency-both-high--and-low-mode-internal-gravity-waves-are-excited-high-modes-propagate-along-curving-characteristics-downward-and-equatorward-the-higher-modes-have-strong-shear-that-results-in-mixing-εz-low-mode-wave-radiation-indicated-in-gray-takes-the-form-of-oscillations-that-propagate-equatorward-upward-characteristics-and-topographic-scattering-have-been-observed-but-the-processes-involved-are-not-completely-understood-from-alford-et-al-2015-modified-from-simmons--alford-2012">
&lt;a data-fancybox="" href="https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/niskine/featured_hu2a35204f8bfe2a2fb0b5d524494f21c4_1070700_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png" data-caption="Schematic showing processes associated with near-inertial generation, dissipation, and propagation. As storms move along the storm track (thick white arrow), a local response occurs with frequencies near the local Coriolis frequency. Both high- and low-mode internal gravity waves are excited. High modes propagate along curving characteristics downward and equatorward. The higher modes have strong shear that results in mixing, ε(z). Low-mode wave radiation (indicated in gray) takes the form of oscillations that propagate equatorward. Upward characteristics and topographic scattering have been observed, but the processes involved are not completely understood. From Alford et al. (2015), modified from Simmons &amp;amp;amp; Alford (2012).">
&lt;img data-src="https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/niskine/featured_hu2a35204f8bfe2a2fb0b5d524494f21c4_1070700_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png" class="lazyload" alt="" width="2086" height="1220">
&lt;/a>
&lt;figcaption>
Schematic showing processes associated with near-inertial generation, dissipation, and propagation. As storms move along the storm track (thick white arrow), a local response occurs with frequencies near the local Coriolis frequency. Both high- and low-mode internal gravity waves are excited. High modes propagate along curving characteristics downward and equatorward. The higher modes have strong shear that results in mixing, ε(z). Low-mode wave radiation (indicated in gray) takes the form of oscillations that propagate equatorward. Upward characteristics and topographic scattering have been observed, but the processes involved are not completely understood. From Alford et al. (2015), modified from Simmons &amp;amp; Alford (2012).
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The Office of Naval Research-sponsored Near Inertial Shear and Kinetic Energy in the North Atlantic experiment (NISKINe) aims at investigating generation, evolution and dissipation of near-inertial waves based on a variety of ship-based and autonomous observations, numerical models and theory. Field work is planned for the Iceland Basin in the North Atlantic, an area of intermittent strong storms, an active mesoscale field in the ocean and a region of strong surface currents, potentially feeding submesoscale dynamics.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Together with my Scripps colleagues Amy Waterhouse and Matthew Alford, and our collaborators Jim Moum from Oregon State University and Harper Simmons from University of Alaska, I am contributing a moored observational component to the project. In May 2019 we deployed an array of three moorings, outfitted with ADCPs, McLane Moored Profilers, thermistors &amp;amp; microcats and turbulence-measuring chipods, in the center of the Iceland Basin. The moorings will provide time series of shear and stratification during times of the field experiment, when a lot of autonomous instruments will be deployed around the moorings, and during the spring and fall storm seasons, when the forcing of near-inertial waves is expected to be strongest.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Propagation of Intra-Seasonal Tropical Oscillations - PISTON</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/piston/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/piston/</guid><description>&lt;p>The oceanographic part of the PISTON experiment aims at better understanding three-dimensional oceanic processes that may influence the propagation of multi- scale convective systems in the atmosphere. Together with collaborators Matthew Alford (Scripps) and Jim Moum (OSU) I deployed two moorings in the tropical western North Pacific on the Palau-Kyushy Ridge from 2018 to 2019. The moorings provide data on ocean velocity, hydrography and turbulence over most of the water column and up into the mixed layer. The measurements will help to constrain heat fluxes in the upper ocean to better understand the exchange of heat with the atmosphere.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Hydraulic Processes in the Samoan Passage</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/hyprsp/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/hyprsp/</guid><description>&lt;p>We just got funded by NSF to study abyssal hydraulic processes in the Samoan Passage. The project will heavily build upon data collected in the
&lt;a href="https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/samoan-passage/">Samoan Passage Abyssal Mixing Experiment&lt;/a>. In addition, we are planning on running a suite of numerical models spanning from idealized 2D to high-resolution 3D runs that will be tuned to observed turbulent mixing. This dataset will help us identify and study a number of processes that are loosely termed &lt;em>hydraulic&lt;/em> - they arise when bottom topography restricts the free flow of the bottom current. Hydraulic processes may cause and alter turbulent mixing of the abyssal current with ambient water and impose restrictions on the maximum flow through the Samoan Passage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Present theory is unable to account for a number of hydraulic aspects that let the flow through Samoan Passage stand out. Among these are flow through connecting channels, flow through channels with two sill configurations and flow across sills with complex bathymetry. Getting a handle on these processes will be important for better understanding the large scale circulation of the Pacific Ocean as the Samoan Passage is the major supplier for deep water renewal in the North Pacific. Moreover, these configurations are by no means unique to the flow through Samoan Passage and a better knowledge of hydraulic processes here will inform research of the flow at many other canyons and fracture zones of the world&amp;rsquo;s oceans.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Flow Encountering Abrupt Topography - FLEAT</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/fleat/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/fleat/</guid><description>&lt;p>The ONR-funded project FLEAT aims at studying interactions of mean-flow and topography in the vicinity of Palau. We try to answer questions like &lt;em>how are energy and momentum of mean and meso-scale flow affected by interactions with bathymetry?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The vicinity of Palau in the tropical North Pacific provides an ideal natural laboratory - steep topography and strong currents make up for exciting experiment sites. In June 2016 we deployed moorings and carried out shipboard measurements with various instruments to study the generation of lee waves and lee vortices as the flow interacted with the northern end of Palau.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Samoan Passage Abyssal Mixing Experiment</title><link>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/samoan-passage/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gunnarvoet.github.io/project/samoan-passage/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Samoan Passage is the major gateway for deep water renewal in the North Pacific where virtually no bottom waters are formed locally.
About 6 Sv (1 Sv $\equiv 1 \times 10^6$ m$^3$ s$^{-1}$), more than half of the abyssal northward limb of the Pacific Meridional Overturning Circulation (MOC), flows through the Samoan Passage while smaller amounts flow across Robbie Ridge to the west and around the Manihiki Plateau to the east.
As the bottom current is forced through the narrow channels and across the sills of the Samoan Passage it is strongly modified by turbulent mixing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the NSF-funded &lt;em>Samoan Passage Abyssal Mixing Experiment&lt;/em> we gathered moored and shipboard measurements to re-assess the long term volume transport through the Samoan Passage and to study flow pathways and turbulent mixing processes in the Samoan Passage.
Moored long-term observations of the abyssal flow through the Samoan Passage, when compared to historical measurements, showed a slightly weakened volume transport by about 0.6 Sv or 10% and a significant warming of $1\times10^{-3}$ K/yr over the past two decades.
Shipboard CTD/LADCP sections from a cruise in 2012 revealed the flow pathways through the Samoan Passage with the unanticipated result of about half the volume transport going through shallower channels to the west while the other, denser, half goes through the main eastern channel.
Topographic sills along both pathways lead to hydraulic response and strong associated acceleration and mixing of the flow.
Detailed measurements at the primary sill of the eastern channel showed flow acceleration to more than 0.5 m/s.
The first direct turbulence measurements with an autonomous Vertical Microstructure Profiler in the Samoan Passage revealed 1000 to 10,000 times stronger turbulence than oceanographic background levels.
Heat-budget derived estimates of turbulent mixing levels were 2 to 6 times higher than area-averaged mixing levels in the Samoan Passage, pointing to the importance of mixing concentrated at so-called hot-spots.
These mixing hot-spots are located downstream of the sills, where the flow, likely hydraulically controlled, accelerates, and hydraulic jumps with the highest mixing levels in the region were observed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>See the
&lt;a href="https://gunnarvoet.github.io/#data" title="Data Section">Data&lt;/a> section for a link to the data archive.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>